Guide to the Ruth Wittenberg Papers MC.95
New York University Archives
Ruth Wittenberg Papers
1961-1972
New York University Archives
Wittenberg, Ruth
MC.95
1 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
Ruth Wittenberg, a long-standing community activist, served on a number of civic organizations associated with the Washington Square neighborhood. These papers concern Washington Square Park and primarily date from the 1960s and 1970s, when the park was renovated.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into three series: I, Washington Square Park rehabilitation project; II, Related material; III, Related publications.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains materials pertaining to citizen and local agency planning, development, and rehabilitation of Washington Square Park during the 1960s and 1970s. Document types include committee minutes, correspondence, designs, press releases, clippings, and background articles.
Biographical Note
Ruth Wittenberg, a long-standing community activist, served on a number of civic organizations concerned with the refurbishing and rehabilitation of Washington Square Park between the years 1964 and 1972. She served as the Vice Chairman of Community Planning Board #2 and as Secretary of the Architects Committee assigned to the rehabilitation of the Park. She also served as reporter of the joint meetings of the Planning Board and Architects Committee.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated to the University Archives by Ruth Wittenberg through Aileen Shaw in 1988.
Washington Square (New York, N.Y.); Minutes (administrative records); Clippings (information artifacts); Urban renewal -- Citizen participation.; Community foundations.; Articles.; New York (N.Y.).; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Invitations.; Brochures.; Washington Square Association; Washington Square Playground Council
- Series I. Washington Square Rehabilitation Project, 1961-1972; .5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Material in Series I relates primarily to the involvement of the Planning Board and Architects Committee in the rehabilitation of Washington Square Park.
  - WSRP--Correspondence, 1961-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - WSRP-Resolutions, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - WSRP-Announcements and Press Releases, 1964-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - WSRP-Minutes and Planning Board #2 and Architecture Committees, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - WSRP-Minutes, 1966-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - WSRP-Minutes, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - WSRP-Minutes, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - WSRP-Architectural Designs, Estimates, and Maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - WSRP-Architectural Designs, Estimates, and Maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wittenberg article: "Washington Square Park: An Important Landmark", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Attendance Sheets-Dated and Undated, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - WSRP--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II. Related Material, 1964-1972; .25 Linear Feet
  Series II contains documents of park-affiliated organizations, including the Washington Square Association and the Washington Square Playground Council.
  - Harry Jackson Exhibit-Invitation and Prospectus, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Recreational Facilities Brochure, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gardening Brochures, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Washington Square Association Minutes and Proposals, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Washington Square Playground/Park Council--Memoranda, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mobile Programs System, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Children Before Dogs Campaign, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Union Square Park Redevelopment Project, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series III. Related Publications, 1962-1971; .25 Linear Feet
  Series III contains original and photocopied newspaper clippings of park rehabilitation developments, as well as a glimpse of community concerns regarding the park's physical and social evolution between 1962 and 1972.
  - WSRP-Newspaper articles, 1962-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - WSRP-Newspaper articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - WSRP-Newspaper articles, originals, 1962-1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)